Finding aid for the Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Կարօ Մինասեան հայկական հավաքածու LSC.1632
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Bound Correspondence: Կազմուած նամակներ, 1856-1932; Series 2.
  - 2.4 Martyros Ter Joakim: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան, 1856-1908
    This subseries contains bound correspondence (with accounts), and includes some unbound letters and notes. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է նամակներ (հաշիւներով), ներառեալ մի քանի անկազմ նամակներ եւ ծանօթագրութի ւններ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1856-1864 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1865-1908 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1869-1874 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1874-1877 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - 2.5 George Mackertich (Bamban): Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանի (Բամբանեան), 1880-1935
    This subseries contains the extensive bound correspondence of George Mackertich. The letters relate to business, stamp and book collection and exchange, family and personal life, evangelical church, and the British and Foreign Bible Society. Materials are in Armenian, English, Persian, and Syriac. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է ծաւալուն Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանի կազմուած նամակներ: Նամակները արեւտրին, դրոշմերի եւ գրքերի հաւաքումին եւ փոխանակութեա նն, ընտանեկան եւ անձնական կեանքին, աւետարանական եկեղեցու, եւ Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութեանն են վերաբերում: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ ասորերէնով են:
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1880-1893 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Baghdad, Bushire, New Julfa.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1894-1896 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: British and Foreign Bible Society, business transactions, and stamps.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1896-1898 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: British and Foreign Bible Society, as well as the buying and selling of stamps.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1896-1900 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: Evangelical church activities
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1898-1900 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: Evangelical church activities and bussiness transactions
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1900-1901 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: bussiness transactions; buying, selling, and records of stamps, acquisition of books, and British and Foreign Bible Society
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1901-1902 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: Evangelical church and its activities, bussiness transactions, and acquisition of books
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1902-1904 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: Armenians in India, family life, such as letters to his mother and other family members. Includes a paper from W.H. Smith and Son addressed to G. Mackertich
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1904 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: stamp exchange and acquisition, family life and letters to family members.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1905 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: bussiness transactions, British and Foreign Bible Society.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1907-1909 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: stamp and book acquisition and exchange; family life and letters to family members, bussiness transactions.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1909-1910 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: stamp acquisition and exchange, bussiness transactions,
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1910-1917 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      New Julfa; content in letters related to: bussiness transactions, British and Foreign Bible society. Includes a white envelope with receipts, notes, and accounting pages.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1912-1913 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Letters in Armenian and English; New Julfa
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1915-1920 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Includes newspaper clippings of automobile and motorbike advertisements.
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1921-1928 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1923-1936 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1928-1935 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 2.6 Melk'um Marcar: Մելքում Մարգար, 1868-1877
    This subseries contains personal and business-related bound correspondence of Melk'um Margar. Materials are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մելքում Մարգարի անձնական եւ արեւտրական կազմուած նամակներ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1868-1877 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 2.7 Martiros Tēr Voskanean (Sarkies): Մարտիրոս Տէր Ոսկանեան (Սարգիսեան), 1894-1912
    This subseries contains 1 book of bound correspondence of Martiros Ter Voskanean (Sarkies), primarily business-related addressed to his brother Tigran. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մարտիրոս Տէր Ոսկանեանի (Սարգիսեան) կազմուած նամակների մի գիրք, մեծ մասամբ արեւտրին վերաբերեալ եւ իր եղբօր Տիգրանին ուղարկուած: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1894-1912 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - 2.8 Armenian Church: Հայկական Եկեղեցին
    This subseries contains two book of bound correspondence of ecclesiastics of the Armenian Church. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայկական եկեղեցու եկեղեցականնե րի կազմուած նամակների երկու գիրք: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1907-1917 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Includes 3 loose pages of Armenian musical notes
    - Collection of Letters: Նամակների հաւաքածոյ, 1930-1932 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Ledgers: Հաշուագրեր, 1829-1951; Series 3.
  This series primarily contains ledgers of various individuals. It also contains accounts, receipts, contracts, deeds, agenda, notes, and other legal and financial documents. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, English, and Dutch. Այս կարգը մեծամասնութեամբ պարունակում է զանազան անհատների հաշուագրեր: Նաեւ պարունակում է հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, պայմանագրեր, կալուածագրեր, ընելիք, ծանօթագրութիւններ, եւ այլ օրինական եւ արեւտրական փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ հոլանդերէնով են:
  - 3.1 M.A. Tēr Georgis: Մ.Ա. Տէր Գէորգեան, 1868-1887
    This subseries contains two ledgers belonging to M.A. Tēr Georgis, and includes some loose receipts and letters. Materials are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մ.Ա. Տէր Գէորգեանին պատկանող երկու հաշուագրեր, ներառեալ մի քանի ստացագրեր եւ նամակներ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1868-1875 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1886-1887 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 3.2 Jani Hovhanisian: Collected Ledgers: Ջանի Յովհանիսեան՝ հաւաքուած հաշուագրեր, 1898-1944
    This subseries contains three ledgers collected by Jani Hovhanisian. Two of the ledgers are in Armenian, and one is in Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում Ջանի Յովհանիսեանի կողմից հաւաքուած երեք հաշուագրեր: Հաշուագրերից երկուսը հայերէնով են, իսկ մէկը՝ պարսկերէնով:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1898 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 3.3 Hovnanian Brothers: Յովնանեան եղբայրներ, 1895-1898
    This subseries contains one ledger belonging to the Hovnanian brothers. The ledger is written in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Յովնանեան եղբայրներին պատկանող մէկ հաշուագիր: Հաշուագիրը հայերէնով է գրուած:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1895-1898 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - 3.4 Martyros Ter Joakim: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան, 1833-1902
    This subseries contains ledgers, accounts, receipts, contracts, and other legal and financial documents belonging to Martyros Tēr Joakim. Materials are mostly in Armenian with some Persian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին պատկանող հաշուագրեր, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, պայմանագրեր, եւ այլ օրինական եւ առեւտրական փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը մեծ մասամբ հայերէնով են, նաեւ՝ պարսկերէնով եւ անգլերէնով:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1833-1838 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1835 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1845-1859 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1846-1847 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Receipts, Contracts, and other legal and financial documents: Ստացագրեր, պայմանագրեր, եւ այլ օրինական եւ արեւտրական փաստաթղթեր, 1858-1874 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Accounts: Հաշիւներ, 1859-1867 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1870-1874 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1895-1902 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - 3.5 Carapiet M. Johannes: Կարապետ Մ. Յովհաննիսեան, 1914-1922
    This subseries contains one ledger, accounts, receipts, and other business-related materials, as well as the last will and testament of Carapiet M. Johannes. Materials are in English and Persian, with some Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Կարապետ Մ. Յովհաննիսեան ի պատկանող մի հաշուագիր, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր եւ այլ արեւտրին վերաբերող նիւթեր, նաեւ իր կտակը: Նիւթերը անգլերէնով եւ պարսկերէնով են՝ նաեւ հայերէնով:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1913 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Accounts, receipts, and other business-related materials: Հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, եւ այլ արեւտրին վերաբերող նիւթեր, 1914-1920 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Will and Testament: Կտակ, 1920-1922 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - 3.6 Margar Karapet: Մարգար Կարապետեան, 1883-1886
    This subseries contains one ledger of Margar Karapet. The ledger is in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մարգար Կարապետեանի մի հաշուագիր: Հաշուագիրը հայերէնով է:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1883-1886 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 3.7 George Mackertich: Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան, 1884-1951
    This subseries contains the many accounts and ledgers of George Mackertich, and also includes notes, agenda, receipts, stamps, letters, and telegraphs. Materials are in Armenian, English, and Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանի շատ հաշիւներ եւ հաշուագրեր, ներառեալ ծանօթագրութի ւններ, ընելիք, ստացագրեր, դրոշմներ, նամակներ եւ հեռագրեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ պարսկերէնով են:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1889-1894 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Ledger (household expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1889-1896 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Ledger (Building account and expenses, Julfa): Հաշուագիր, 1890 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1891-1893 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1894 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1896 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Ledger (household expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1884-1897 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1885-1886 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1889-1891 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Accounts and notes: Հաշիւներ եւ ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1898 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1922 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Ledger (home and other expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1924-1925 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Accounts and Notes: Հաշիւներ եւ ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1924-1925 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1925 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1926 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1926-1927 (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Ledgers (cinema accounts): Հաշուագրեր, 1927-1929 (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1927-1930 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Ledger (food expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1928-1929 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Ledger (rental expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1929-1930 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Ledger (accounts with Chas. E.G. Tisdall): Հաշուագիր, 1902 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1929-1931 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1929-1933 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Ledger and notes: Հաշուագիր եւ ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1930 (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Ledger (accounts with individuals): Հաշուագիր, 1930-1931 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1931-1932 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1932 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Ledger (food expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - Ledger (repairs to Julfa house): Հաշուագիր, 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - Ledger (repairs to Julfa house): Հաշուագիր, 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - Ledger (food expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - Ledger (accounts with N.J. Gambini): Հաշուագիր, 1902 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Accounts (repairs to Julfa house): Հաշիւներ, 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - Ledger (education expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1903-1927 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1906 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Ledgers and Agenda books: Հաշուագրէր եւ ընելիք, 1910-1920 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Ledger and Agenda book: Հաշուագիր եւ ընելիք, 1913-1914 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1918-1921 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Ledger (Fereiden Trip expenses): Հաշուագիր, 1932-1933 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Book of Telegraphs: Հեռագրերի գիրք (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Letter and Account from Hohannēs Harowt'iwn: Նամակ եւ հաշիւ Յոհաննէս Յարութիւնի կողմից, 1934 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Account book and notes: Հաշուագիր եւ ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1935 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Accounts (wedding expenses): Հաշիւներ, 1938 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1938-1941 (Box 24, Folder 6)
      includes some stamps: ներառեալ մի քանի դրոշմներ
    - Ledger (accounts with individuals): Հաշուագիր, 1943-1951 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Accounts (Suleiman): Հաշիւներ, 1944 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Receipts: Ստացագրեր (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - 3.8 Miscellaneous: Զանազան, 1854-1934
    This subseries contains ledgers belonging to several different individuals. Materials are in Armenian, English, Dutch, and Russian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի քանի անհատներին պատկանող հաշուագրեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, հոլանդերէնով, եւ պարսկերէնով են:
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1854-1864 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1864-1868 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Ledger (S.M.Terunts' ): Հաշուագիր, 1875-1877 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1875-1882 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Ledger and Accounts: Հաշուագիր եւ հաշիւներ, 1876-1917 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Ledger (S.M.Terunts' ): Հաշուագիր (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Ledger (S.M.Terunts' ): Հաշուագիր, 1878-1880 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Ledger (S.M.Terunts' and Boekoe Sapie): Հաշուագիր, 1879-1888 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Accounts: Հաշիւներ, 1891-1893 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Ledger (Mirza Sarkis): Հաշուագիր (Միրզա Սարգիս), 1896 (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1899 (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - Ledger (T'adēos Nazarēt'ean): Հաշուագիր: Հաշուագիր (Թադէոս Նազարէթեան), 1907-1934 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 1857-1890 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Ledger: Հաշուագիր, 19th century (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - 3.9 Business and Commerce documents: Առեւտրական եւ վաճառականական փաստաթղթեր, 1829-1933
    This subseries contains various business and commerce documents, including correspondence, accounts, receipts, deeds, and other financial documents. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, English, and Dutch. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան արեւտրական եւ վաճառականակա ն փաստաթղթեր, ներառեալ նամակներ, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, կալուածագրեր, եւ այլն: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ հոլանդերէնով են:
    - Letters, accounts, receipts and other financial documents: Նամակներ, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, եւ այլ արեւտրական փաստաթղթեր, 1829-1888 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Letters, accounts, receipts and other financial documents: Նամակներ, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, եւ այլ արեւտրական փաստաթղթեր, 1831-1928 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Letters, accounts, receipts and other financial documents: Նամակներ, հաշիւներ, ստացագրեր, եւ այլ արեւտրական փաստաթղթեր, 1880-? (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Booklet of letters and receipts: Նամակների եւ ստացագրերի գրքոյկ, 1891 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Bank receipts: Դրամատունի ստացագրեր, 1912-1933 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Diaries: Օրագրեր, 1845-1935; Series 4.
  This series contains mostly diaries of various individuals with their daily activities and accounts. There are also some official documents. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, English, and French. Այս կարգը պարունակում է զանազան անհատների օրագրեր, ներառեալ իրենց գործունէութիւններ եւ հաշիւներ: Պաշտօնական փաստաթղթեր ալ կան: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ ֆրանսերէնով են:
  - 4.1 Minas Aghanur: Մինաս Աղանուր, 1865-1871
    This subseries contains one diary of Minas Aghanur comprising his activities along with some business accounts. The diary is written in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մինաս Աղանուրի մի օրագիր, ներառեալ իր գործունէութի ւններ եւ արեւտրական հաշիւներ: Օրագիրը հայերէնով է գրուած:
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1865-1871 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - 4.2 Maryros Ter Joakim: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան, 1845-1850
    This subseries contains one diary, one small ledger, and some accounts of Martyros Ter Joakim. The materials pertain mostly to Martyros Ter Joakims activities, and contain information regarding the Armenian Apostolic church in Calcutta. Materials are in Armenian. Այս եպթակարգը պարունակում է Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին պատկանող մի օրագիր, մի հաշուագիր, եւ մի քանի հաշիւներ: Նիւթերը Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին գործունէութի ւններուն են վերաբերում, ներառեալ կալկաթայում Հայկական Առաքելական եկեղեցւոյ մասին տեղեկութիւնն եր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Diary, ledger, and accounts: Օրագիր, հաշուագիր, եւ հաշիւներ, 1845-1850 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - 4.3 George Mackertich (Bamban): Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան, 1879-1934
    This subseries contains diaries of George Mackertich, including information relating to his travels to Odessa, Baghdad, Africa, Indonesia, and other places. There is also information pertaining to chemical measurements for Photography, handwritten excerpts copied from a book, accounts, and a report on the Eastern Equatorial Africa Mission. Materials are in English, with some Armenian and Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Գէւորգ Մկրտիչեանի օրագրեր, ներառեալ իր ճամբորդոթիւն ներուն մասին տեղեկութիւն Օդեսայում, Բաղդադում, Ափրիկէյում, եւ Ինդոնէզիայու մ եւ այլ տեղերում: Նաեւ կան լուսանկարչու թեան վերաբերող չափեր, գրքից օրինակուած հատուածներ, հաշիւներ, եւ Արեւելեան հասարակածայի ն Ափրիկէ առաքելութեան մասին մի տեղեկագրութի ւն: Նիւթերը անգլերէնով են՝ մի քիչ հայերէնով եւ պարսկերէնով:
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1880 (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Begins at Odessa, 1st of January
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1881 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Account of Baghdad from February to November
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1882 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Account of Baghdad
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1883 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Diary, with measurements relating to Photography and handwritten excerpts copied from a book: Օրագիր, ներառեալ լուսանկարչութեան վերաբերող չափեր եւ գրքից օրինակուած հատուածներ, 1879 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1883-1885 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Baghdad; journey to Urumia
    - Report on the Eastern Equatorial Africa Mission: Արեւելեան հասարակածային Ափրիկէ առաքելութեան մասին տեղեկագրութիւն, 1897 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1911 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Diary: Օրագիր, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      In Indonesia and Karachi
  - 4.4 Hovsēp' Mkrtich'ean: Յովսէփ Մկրտիչեան, 1915-1936
    This subseries contains a passport, and travel, business, and other official documents belonging to Hovsēp' Mkrtich'ean. Materials are in Persian, Armenian, and French. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Յովսէփ Մկրտիչեանին պատկանող մի անցնագիր եւ ճամբորդական, արեւտրական եւ այլ պաշտօնական փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը պարսկերէնով, հայերէնով, եւ ֆրանսերէնով են:
    - Hovsēp' Mkrtich'ean: Յովսէփ Մկրտիչեան, 1935 (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Persian letters and documents: Պարսկերէն լեզուով նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր:, 1604-1967; Series 5.
  This extensive series contains materials primarily in the Persian language (with some Armenian and English). Materials include correspondence, Firmans (royal decrees), title deeds, receipts, many business related and official documents, as well as notes and documents on historical events and places. Of special note are the Firmans from various Shahs, and the antiquity of some of the materials. Այս մեծածաւալ կարգը պարունակում է գլխաւորապէս պարսկերէն լեզուով փաստաթղթեր, նաեւ մի քիչ հայերէն եւ անգլերէն: Կան նամակներ, ֆարմաններ (արքայական հրամանագրեր), կալուածագրեր, ստացագրեր, շատ արեւտրական եւ պաշտօնական փաստաթղթեր, նաեւ ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ փաստաթղթեր, որոնք պատմական դէպքերին եւ տեղերին են վերաբերում: Նշանակալից են զանազան Շահերի կողմից ֆարմանները եւ նիւթերի հնութիւնը:
  - 5.1 Letters: Նամակներ, 1825-1913
    This subseries contains business and personal letters, documents, and receipts, including information pertaining to Persian laws. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է արեւտրական եւ անձնական նամակներ, փաստաթղթեր, եւ ստացագրեր, ներառեալ պարսկական օրէնքների վերաբերող տեղեկութիւն:
    - Business letters: Արեւտրական նամակներ, 1825-1913 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Letters and documents: Նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1852-1912 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Letters regarding silver mining and its laws: Արծաթի հանքերի եւ նրանց օրէնքների վերաբերեալ նամակներ, 1899-1907 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Business letters and documents: Առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Business letters and documents: Առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Business letters and documents: Առեւտրական նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Letters and receipts: Նամակներ եւ ստացագրեր (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - 5.2 Zill-us-Sultan: Զիլուս Սուլթան, 1874-1967
    This subseries contains correspondence, telegrams (with photographs and negatives of the telegram), Firmans, and receipts connected with Mascud Mirza Zill-us-Sultan, the governor of Isfahan. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մասկուտ Միրզա Զիլուս Սուլթանի (Սպահանի կառավարիչը) կապուած նամակներ, հեռագիրներ (ներառեալ հեռագրից նկարներ եւ ֆիլմեր), հրամանագրեր (Ֆարմաններ), եւ ստացագրեր:
    - Telegram; photographs and negative of the telegram: Հեռագիր. հեռագրից նկարներ եւ ֆիլմեր, 1906 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, documents, and receipts: Նամակներ, փաստաթղթեր, եւ ստացագրեր, 1912-1967 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and documents: Նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1874-1911 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Firmans: Հրամանագրեր, 1898 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      This Firman refers to Gongin, the goldsmith granting him the title of "Mirza Gongin Khan" for his destinction in his art, at Julfa 1316. H.Qhamari, seal signature. Presented by Mr. Abraham Aghabegian, 8.5.47 Tehran
  - 5.3 Mulla Ali Mirpanj: Մուլլա Ալի Միրփանջ, 1861-1912
    This subseries contains letters and documents connected with Mulla Ali Mirpanj. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մուլլա Ալի Միրփանջի կապուած նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր:
    - Letters and documents: Նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1861-1912 (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - 5.4 Fathali Shah: Ֆատհալի Շահ, 1797-1950
    This subseries contains Firmans and documents connected with various Shahs. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան Շահերի կապուած հրամանագրեր (ֆարմաններ) եւ փաստաթղթեր:
    - Firman: հրամանագիր, 1797 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Firmans of Fath-Ali Shah Qajar: Ֆատհալի Շահ հրամանագրեր, 1896-1897 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Firman of Fathali Shah Ghajar: Ֆատհալի Շահ Ղաջարի հրամանագիր, 1936-1950 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - 5.5 Historical notes and documents: Պատմական ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1959